Preliminary Inventory of the Joseph Goebbels papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph Goebbels papers
1884-1945
47004
Hoover Institution Archives
11 manuscript boxes, 7 microfilm reels, 1 sound tape reel (6.4 linear feet)
Diaries, correspondence, academic and fictional writings, school notebooks, personal documents, memoranda and expense accounts, and sound recording of a speech relating to the early life of Joseph Goebbels, and to activities of the Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei and of the German government during World War II, especially military and political affairs. Includes diaries from 1925 August 12 to 1926 October 27, from 1942 January 27 to 1943 December 9 (incomplete), and for 1944 October 3; and sound recording of a speech, entitled "Discorso al Campo di Maggio," 1937 September 28. Also includes microfilm and/or photocopies of all original diaries and of other original documents.
Goebbels, Joseph, 1897-1945.
Access
Original diaries and other original documents (Boxes 1-7 and Box 8, Folder 5) closed. Microfilm and/or photocopies available for use.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1947, with additional materials added through 2013.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
German national socialist leader; minister of public enlightenment and propaganda, 1933 to 1945.
Scope and Contents note
Diaries, correspondence, academic and fictional writings, school notebooks, personal documents, memoranda and expense accounts, and sound recording of a speech relating to the early life of Joseph Goebbels, and to activities of the Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei and of the German government during World War II, especially military and political affairs. Includes diaries from 1925 August 12 to 1926 October 27, from 1942 January 27 to 1943 December 9 (incomplete), and for 1944 October 3; and sound recording of a speech, entitled "Discorso al Campo di Maggio," 1937 September 28. Also includes microfilm and/or photocopies of all original diaries and of other original documents.
Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei.; National socialism.; Propaganda, German.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; Germany--Politics and government--1933-1945.; Statesmen--Germany.; Audiotapes.
- DIARIES (Originals), 1925-1944
  - Fragments of diaries (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1925 August 12 - 1926 October 27 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Photocopies pages 5 and 6, 1941? (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1942 January 27-30 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - 1942 January 31-February 6 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - 1942 February 7-13 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - 1942 February 14-19 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - 1942 February 20-25 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - 1942 February 26-March 3 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - 1942 March 4-9 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 1942 March 10-16 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - 1942 March 17-20 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - 1942 March 21-29 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - 1942 March 30-April 6 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - 1942 April 7-14 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - 1942 April 15-20 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - 1942 April 21-25 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - 1942 April 26-29 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - 1942 April 30-May 5 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - 1942 May 6-11 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - 1942 May 12-18 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - 1942 May 19-23 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - 1942 July 20 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - 1942 December 7-15 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - 1942 December 16-20; 1943 January 2, March 1-2 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - 1943 March 3-9 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - 1943 March 10-12 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - 1943 March 13-18 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - 1943 March 19-21, April 9-13 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - 1943 April 14-20 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - 1943 April 21-28 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - 1943 April 29-May 8 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - 1943 May 9-11 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - 1943 May 12-16 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - 1943 May 17-22 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - 1943 May 23-28, July 25-26 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - 1943 July 27-29, September 8 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - 1943 September 9-11 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - 1943 September 12-16 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - 1943 September 17-22 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - 1943 September 23 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - 1943 September 24-30 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - 1943 November 1-7 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - 1943 November 8-13 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - 1943 November 14-19 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - 1943 November 20-25 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - 1943 November 26-30 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - 1943 December 4-9 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - 1944 October 3 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Photocopies, 1943 February 14-23 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Photocopies, 1943 April 1-6, 9-30 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Photocopy, 1943 June 6 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Photocopies, 1943 September 23-30 (Box-folder 8: 4)
- MISCELLANEA, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 8: 5)
- PHOTOCOPIES (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - 2 items dealing with property tax on Schwanenwerder, 1939 (Item 1)
  - Eyewitness report of Lilli Ernst about police brutality against Goebbels, 1931 June (Item 2)
  - 2 letters from tax attorney Paul Schueber dealing with income tax problems, 1933 (Item 3)
  - 2 letters from August Boch to Goebbels, 1932 December, 1933 November (Item 4)
    Scope and Contents note
    December letter offers a small book outlining the memoirs of the Spanish ambassador in St. Petersburg in the summer of 1914.
  - Goebbels letter of condolence to Frau Troost, 1934 January (Item 5)
  - Letter of Vereinigte Krankenversicherung Aktiengesellschaft to Goebbels accounting for some dividends, 1936 June (Item 6)
  - List of parts of uniform to be worn at the Reichsparteitag, 1939 (Item 7)
  - Letter from Magda Goebbels' secretariat, requesting information from Goebbels' secretariat whether she should accept invitation to Reichsparteitag, 1939 August (Item 8)
  - List of clothing donation from various Goebbels households, 1942 June (Item 9)
  - Accounts for a Goebbels trip to the Fuehrerhaupt Quartier, 1943 March (Item 10)
  - Note from Hinkel (?) reminding Goebbels about the birthdays of various personalities, 1942 September (Item 11)
  - Instructions to courier to pick up three guests and a set of motion picture films to be taken out to Lanke, 1943 October (Item 12)
  - Letter of Wilhelm Murr, Stuttgart, that he is sending fresh fruits from his commercial farm, 1943 November (Item 13)
  - Breakfast invitation from Dr. Lammers, 19?? February (Item 14)
  - List of monthly income of Goebbels and list of money given to Mrs. Goebbels, undated (Item 15)
  - Draft of letter of congratulations to Goering on his 50th birthday, 1943 January (Item 16)
  - Statement and list of furniture and carpets that were moved from Schwanenwerder to Lanke, 1943 August (Item 17)
  - List of duties of the reorganised household staff in Lanke, 1943 December (Item 18)
  - Attached to previous material, note to Streicher from Goebbels, Christmas, 1934 (Item 19)
  - Exchange of greetings between Goebbels and Rearadmiral von Puttkammer, undated (Item 20)
  - Draft and final telegram of congratulations to Fritz Darges on his marriage, 1944 May (Item 21)
  - Letter of congratulations to Gustaf Frensen on his 80th birthday, 1943 October (Item 22)
  - Exchange of congratulations with Ambassador von Jagow, Budapest, 1944 March (Item 23)
  - Draft of telegram of congratulations to Professor Clemens Krauss, Director of State Opera Munich, undated (Item 24)
  - Telegram of congratulations (and card noting thanks) to Professor Dr. Heide upon his 50th birthday, 1944 April (Item 25)
  - Draft of letter to Wilhelm Schepmann, Head of the SA, congratulating him on his 50th birthday, and Schepmann's reply, 1944 June (Item 26)
  - Telegram to Xavier Schwarz congratulating him on his birthday, and Schwarz's reply, 1944 November (Item 27)
  - Small file (in Abschrift) dealing with purchases of paintings, 1944 August - 1945 January (Item 28)
- MICROFILM OF DIARIES, 1925-1943 (Microfilm cabinet)
  - 1925 August 12 - 1926 October 27 (Reel 7)
  - 1942 January 21 - March 12 (pg. 23) (Reel 1)
  - 1942 March 12 (p. 24) - April 29 (p. 32) (Reel 2)
  - 1942 April 30 - 1943 March 12 (p. 28) (Reel 3)
  - 1943 March 13 - May 25 (p. 25) (Reel 4)
  - 1943 May 25 (p. 26) - November 12 (p. 11) (Reel 5)
  - 1943 November 12 (p. 11) - December 9 (p. 26) (Reel 6)
- SOUND TAPE REEL (Tape cabinet)
  - Speech, "Discorso al Campo di Maggio,", 1937 September 28
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS
  - Diary, 1942 March 24 (Box-folder 8: 7)
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS ADDED IN 2013 (Boxes 9-11)
  - Corrected typescript of novel "Michael Voorman,", 1930 (Box 9, File 1)
  - Notebooks, report cards, and other school-related materials, 1900-1927 (Box 9, File 2)
  - Diary, poems, college study book, "History of Art in the 19th Century,", 1920s (Box 9, File 3)
  - College study book, seminary, Freiburg, "Introduction to Philosophy,", 1919 (Box 9, File 4)
  - Diary, college study book, signed multiple times Joseph Goebbels, 1915-1916 (Box 9, File 5)
  - College study book, signed twice Joseph Goebbels and multiple times Anka Stalherm in Goebbels' handwriting, Bonn/Freiburg; Goethe's Faust, psychology, history, "Monologue of Judas Iscariot,", 1918 (Box 9, File 6)
  - College study book, poems, Freiburg, 1919 (Box 9, File 7)
  - College study book, multiple poems, signed multiple times, Wuerzburg, winter semester, 1918-1919 (Box 9, File 8)
  - College study book, Heidelberg, winter semester, 1920-1921 (Box 9, File 9)
  - High school note book, letter to his teacher regarding the loss of his sister Elisabeth, short essay or diary entry (?) signed multiple times, 1901-1915 (Box 9, File 10)
  - Journal; study book; "Wilhelm Raabe" essay; poems, signed multiple times, including "Munich, Christmas 1918, Dr. Joseph Goebbels,", 1916, 1918 (Box 9, File 11)
  - High school study book, German, Rheydt, "utraque fortuna" school essay with the grade "gut,", 1916 (Box 9, File 12)
  - Disbound essay, "Theodor Storm the Poet, for his 100. Birthday," signed "P. Joseph Goebbels,", 1917 September 14 (Box 9, File 13)
  - Dissertation, faculty of philosophy, Heidelberg University, "Whilhelm v. Schuetz as Dramatist, History of the Romantic Drama," signed "Paul Joseph Goebbels" Rheydt, 1921 (Box 9, File 14)
  - Disbound, "Study of Goethe,", undated (Box 9, File 15)
  - High school study book, algebra, signed multiple times, 1916 (Box 9, File 16)
  - Disbound narrative, "Those Who Love the Sun" (Die die Sonne lieben), 1917 (Box 10, File 17)
  - Disbound book, Sowing (Die Saat), play in three acts, 1920 (Box 10, File 18)
  - Disbound notes, poem, shorthand notes, undated (Box 10, File 19)
  - Notebook, "The Mother's Prayer" (Der Mutter Gebet - Ein Idyll aus dem Kriege), signed multiple times, 1917-1918 (Box 10, File 20)
  - Journal, lecture, "Extracts from German Contemporary Literature" (Ausschnitte aus der deutschen Literatur der Gegenwart, Moderne Tierpoeten), 1920s (Box 10, File 21)
  - Journal, drama, "Struggle of the Working Class" (Kampf der Arbeiterklasse), 1919 (Box 10, File 22)
  - Journal, "Political Diary" (Politisches Tagebuch), undated (Box 10, File 23)
  - Journal, novel, Gypsy Blood (Zigeunerblut), signed "P. J. Goebbels stud. germ. Bonn,", 1910s (Box 10, File 24)
  - Journal, poem, love letters, signed multiple times, Rheydt, 1916 (Box 10, File 25)
  - Disbound journal, study book, Goethe, history, poems, school schedule, 1918 (Box 10, File 26)
  - Journal, small vocabulary study book, poems "November Afternoon" (Novembernachmittag), "Distress" (Die Not), 1915-1925 (Box 10, File 27)
  - Journal, novel, Michael Voormann: A Man's Fate in the Pages of a Diary "I dedicate this in memory of my friend Richard Flisges," handwritten original manuscript, 1923 (Box 10, File 28)
  - Journal, novel, Michael Voormann's Teenage Years, III. Part (Michael Voormann Jugendjahre III. Teil), 1919 (Box 10, File 29)
  - Journal, drama, Heinrich Kaempfert, a drama in three acts, 1919 (Box 10, File 30)
  - Disbound, mostly poems, some notes, undated (Box 10, File 31)
  - 20 letters to Goebbels, 1915-1929 (Box 10, File 32)
  - 9 letters; 2 cards, Lene Krage to Goebbels, 42pp.; 1 envelope with 2 notes; 45 letters, mostly from Werl, from multiple persons to Goebbels, i.e. Agnes Koelsch, Liesel, 1916-1922 (Box 11, File 33)
  - 24 letters from Theo Gutmann to Goebbels, 1918-1920 (Box 11, File 34)
  - Family correspondence, 18 letters from father, 3 letters from brother Hans, 2 letters from sister Maria, 1 postcard, signed "D.M." including greetings from father and others, 1918-1923 (Box 11, File 35)
  - Diverse documents, 1918-1929 (Box 11, File 36)
    Baptismal certificate for brother Hans Goebbels; vaccination card, sister Maria Goebbels; death notice, Hans Prang, Rheydt; 5 telegrams to Joseph Goebbels; 1 telegram to Hans Goebbels; letter from Albertus-Magnus-Verein to Joseph Goebbels; letter from Westdeutsche Landeszeitung to Joseph Goebbels; annual report, Albertus-Magnus-Verein; receipt over 700 Mark for Joseph Goebbels, Rheydt; legal document regarding a property sale between Mr. Clegg and Mr. Oehmen; school essay, Joseph Goebbels; publishing contract between Joseph Goebbels and Xenien-Verlag, Leipzig.
  - 22 Fielpost letters to Goebbels, 1915-1918 (Box 11, File 37)
  - 41 letters from different people, including Hubert Hompsch, Willy Zilles, Liesel, Agnes, Voss, Theo Gutmann, 1914-1918 (Box 11, File 38)
  - 6 letters from Olgi Esenwein to Goebbels, 1924 (Box 11, File 39)
  - 26 letters from Richard Fliesges to Goebbels, 1917-1922 (Box 11, File 40)
  - Disbound, handwritten observations, poems, notes, essays, including "Farewell to Bonn,", 1916-1917 (Box 11, File 41)
  - Printed matter, 1923, undated (Box 11, File 42)
    Newspaper, Koelner Tageblatt, Saturday, June 23, 1923; student information flyer about war bonds, folio, 4pp.; newspaper clipping, "The Cause of the Buehnevolksbund" (Buehnenvolksbund was the sponsor of touring theater companies that performed in a national and Christian spirit), article written by Dr. Goebbels, Rheydt.
  - Disbound, partial school essay, 1917-1918 (Box 11, File 43)
  - Diverse documents, 1920-1921 (Box 11, File 44)
    3 small envelopes, two containing hair from Anka Stalherm; 115 letters, 324 pp., 2 postcards, correspondence between Goebbels and Anka Stalherm, beginning February 4, 1918, last dated letter October 15, 1920; 7 various letters to and from Goebbels.
  - One envelope, "Anka" to "Ulex," containing several small clipped notes, a clipped invoice from a hospital, undated (Box 11, File 45)
  - Booklet, "The Berghof Before Its Destruction," 14 interior black and white photographs of Adolf Hitler's Berghof at Obersalzberg, 3.5" x 2.5", Verlag M. Bauer, Munich, undated (Box 11, File 46)